<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[An, A,B,C, wyth a cathechisme, that is to saye, an instruction to be learned of euerye chylde before he be brought to be confyrmed ...] [sette forth by thee Kinges Maiestye ; whereunto is also ioyned the letany and suffrages].</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S554</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21633774</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21633774</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24848</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09736)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24848)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1761:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[An, A,B,C, wyth a cathechisme, that is to saye, an instruction to be learned of euerye chylde before he be brought to be confyrmed ...] [sette forth by thee Kinges Maiestye ; whereunto is also ioyned the letany and suffrages].</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10] + p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted at London in Fletestrete at the signe of the Sunne, ouer agaynst the Conduyte, by Edwarde Whytchurche,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.LI. [1551]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.p. lacking; title suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum"--Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: fragment; pages torn with loss of print; leaves 2,4,5,7 and 8 of last quire only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
               <term>Prayers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:24848:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 146 -->
            <opener>Let vs praye.</opener>
            <p>O God, mercyfull father, that deſpiſeſt not the ſigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of a contrite hart, nor the deſyre of ſoch as be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, mercyfully aſſyſt our praiers that we make before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in al our troubles and aduerſities, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they oppreſſe vs: And graciouſly heare vs, that thoſe euils which the craf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; ſubteltye of the deuyll or ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worcketh agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt vs be brought to naught &amp; by the prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes thei may be dyſperſed <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeruauntes, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>t, 
<pb facs="tcp:24848:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 147 -->
beyng hurt by no perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, may euermore geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes vnto the, in thi ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly church, through Ieſus chriſt our lorde. amen.</p>
            <p>O lorde aryſe, helpe vs, and dely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer vs for thy names ſake.</p>
            <p>O God, we haue hearde wyth our eares, &amp; oure fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue declared vnto vs the noble workes that thou dyddeſt in theyr day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, &amp; in thee olde tyme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them.</p>
            <p>O lord aryſe, helpe vs, &amp; deliuer vs, for thyne honour.</p>
            <p>Glorye to the father. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As it was in the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is and euer ſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:24848:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 148 -->
alway hauing ſufficyent, maye be rych and ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful in all good workes throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe oure lorde Ieſu chriſt Amen.</p>
            <p>Lord haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs Chriſt haue merci vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs Lord haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs Our father &amp;c. &amp; let vs not be led into te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacion. But deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euyl. Lorde heare my prayer. And let my cry come to the. From the fir<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the de<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>il <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> oure
<pb facs="tcp:24848:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 148 -->
chriſtes ſake. Amen.</p>
            <p>ALmighti god, which haſt geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs grace at this time with one accord to make our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>catyons vnto the, &amp; doeſte promiſe that when two or three bee gathered in thy name, thou wylt graunte their requeſtes: fulfil now O Lord, thee deſyres &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes as may be moſt expedient for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting vs in thys worlde, knowledge of thy <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>th, &amp; in the world to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>e, lyfe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:24848:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 149 -->
            <head>¶Certayne graces to bee ſayde before and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meate.</head>
            <div type="preprandial_grace">
               <head>Grace before dyner.</head>
               <p>THe eyes of al thinges do loke vp &amp; truſte in the, O Lorde: Thou ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt them meate in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon. Thou doeſte open thy hand, and fylleſt with thy bleſſing, euery liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thing Good lorde bleſſe vs &amp; all thy gyftes, whyche we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue of thy bounteous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie. Through chriſt our lorde. Amen.</p>
               <p>The king of eternal glor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> make vs perteners of the
<pb facs="tcp:24848:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 149 -->
heauenly table. amen.</p>
               <p>God is charitie, &amp; he that dwelleth in charitie, dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth in god, &amp; god in him, god graunt vs all to dwel in hym. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postprandial_grace">
               <head>Grace after dyner.</head>
               <p>THe god of peace and loue, vouchſafe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wai to dwel with vs. And thou lord haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, glory, honour, &amp; praiſe be to the, O God, whyche haſt fed vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our tender age, &amp; g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>nce to e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wyth
<pb facs="tcp:24848:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 150 -->
the lyfe euerlaſtynge, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe oure Lord Ieſus chryſt. amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="preprandial_grace">
               <head>Grace before dyner or ſupper.</head>
               <p>PRayſed bee thou oure moſte mercifull &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father which of thy ineſtimable goodnes haſt geuen thy moſt dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſus to payn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful deth for our ſakes, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by not al only deliueringe vs &amp; al faithful from euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting death &amp; damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but alſo purchaſing vnto vs euerlaſting lyfe, ioye &amp; felicite: ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de we beſech the thy holye ſpirite into our
<pb facs="tcp:24848:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 151 -->
hartes that we may daily more and more walke and go forward in the pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pathwayes of thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lawes and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postprandial_grace">
               <head>After dyner or ſupper.</head>
               <p>NOw you haue wel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed youre bodyes remember the lamentable afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; miſeries of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye thouſandes of youre neighbours &amp; brethren in chriſt, viſited by the hand of god, ſome with mortall plages, and diſeaſes ſome with impriſonment, ſome wyth extreme pouertye &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:24848:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 152 -->
                  <pb facs="tcp:24848:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 152 -->
neceſſitye, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eyther they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not or they haue not to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ede on as ye haue done, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre therfore how moch and how depely ye preſent are bound to the goodnes of almighty god, for your health, welthe, lybertye, &amp; manye other hys benefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes geuen vnto you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="responsorial_prayer">
               <head>Reſponce.</head>
               <p>Graces and thankes, be now vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym &amp; alwayes, for theſe and al other hys benefytes ſo mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, louingly and aboundantly powred vpon vs. amen</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:24848:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 153 -->God ſaue our Kynge and the Realme, and ſend vs peace in chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprinted at London in Fleteſtrete at the ſigne of the Sunne, ouer agaynſt the Conduyte, By Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde Whyt-churche.</p>
            <p>M.D.LI.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>Cum Priuilegio ad Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum Solum</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:24848:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 153 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
